Elias Lieberman Papers
Elias Lieberman Papers
1916-1966
Lieberman, Elias, 1883-1969.
45 items (ca.) (SC)
Papers of the American poet, educator. Born in St. Petersburg, Russia. Winner of the James Joyce Award, 1966. Biographical material, correspondence (1918-1963), memorabilia, and writings, which includes poems (1916-1966) both by Lieberman and by others. Also included is a manuscript by James Huneker that may be a book review. Correspondents include William S. Braithwaite, the Century Company, Charles Scribner's Sons, Maria Catarina Lombard, James H. McCormick, Piney Woods Country Life School, Karl Schmidt, Samuel Shipman, James S. Taylor, University of Buffalo's Lockwood Memorial Library, University of Kentucky's Margaret I. King Library, and Stephen S. Wise.
149135
Biographical History
Elias Lieberman (1883-1969) was an American poet and educator, best known for his poem "I Am An American."
Lieberman was born in St. Petersburg, Russia on October 30, 1883 to Nathan David and Sophia (Elbaum) Lieberman. The family immigrated to America in 1891. Upon graduating from the City College of New York with his A.B. in 1903, Lieberman began working as an English teacher at a public school. Lieberman went on to earn his M.A. (1906) and Ph.D. (1911) from New York University. On July 1, 1913, he married Rose Kiesler with whom he had two children, Amy and James. After years of working as an English teacher and high school principal, Lieberman accepted a position with the New York Board of Education in 1940, as an associate superintendent of schools in charge of the junior high school division.
Lieberman's first major publication was American Short Story, published in 1912, followed by Paved Streets, published in 1918. He was a member of the Poetry Society of America and served as a judge for various national poetry contests. Lieberman also worked as an associate editor for Puck, literary editor for The American Hebrew, and contributing editor for Current Literature. He died on July 13, 1969 in South Richmond Hill, NY.
Selected Works
1912 American Short Story
1918 Paved Streets
1926 Poetry for Junior High Schools
1930 Ancient Mariner and Poems of the Sea (editor) Hand Organ Man
1931 Poems for Enjoyment
1940 Man in the Shadows
1954 To My Brothers Everywhere
1976 Notation in Haste
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Elias Lieberman Papers contains Biographical material, Correspondence, Memorabilia, and Writings from the American poet.
Biographical material consists of biographical notes on Lieberman, as well as award announcements and reviews of some of Lieberman's works (copies of these reviews are also located in the Writings series).
Most pieces of Correspondence in the collection are incoming letters regarding Lieberman's works, although two of the letters are matched with Lieberman's reply.
Memorabilia consists of a variety of materials related to Lieberman's life and works, such as an advertisement for a recording of Lieberman reading "I Am An American" and "To My Brother's Everywhere," programs for events honoring Lieberman's achievements, and Lieberman's bookplates.
The final series, Writings, consists of both Lieberman's works and works written by others. With the exception of a single newspaper clipping from the New York Times, "School in the Good Old Days," all of Lieberman's works in the collection are pieces of poetry. The Works by others subseries mainly consists of reviews of Lieberman's works produced in pamphlet form (copies of these reviews are also located in the Biographical material series). The subseries also contains a manuscript of James Huneker that may be a book review.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains four series: Biographical material, Correspondence, Memorabilia, and Writings. The Correspondence is arranged chronologically, while the Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type (i.e. advertisements, bookplates, programs, tributes). Writings is divided into two subseries, Works by Lieberman and Works by others, within which materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
The E. P. Dutton & Company, Inc. Records contains production and publicity materials related to Elias Lieberman's To My Brothers Everywhere, published by E. P. Dutton & Company in 1954.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962.; Lieberman, Elias, 1883-1969 -- Archives.; Lombard, Maria Catarina.; McCormick, James H.; Schmidt, Karl.; Shipman, Samuel, 1883-1937.; Wise, Stephen Samuel, 1874-1949.; Century Company.; Charles Scribner's Sons.; Piney Woods School.; State University of New York at Buffalo, University Libraries.; University of Kentucky, Libraries.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- Jewish authors.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Educators -- United States.; Jews, American.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Advertising fliers.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Poems.; Programs (documents); Educators.; Poets.; Huneker, James, 1857-1921.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elias Lieberman, 1964 and 1966.
James Gibbons Huneker manuscript gift of Elias Lieberman, 1967.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - New York Supervisor, 1954 (Sc 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Sc 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence
  - 13 Nov 1918 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 31 Dec 1919 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 24 Oct 1921, envelope included (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 31 Dec 1921, envelope included (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 23 Jan 1923 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 19 May 1923 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 04 Feb 1926 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 17 May 1926 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 16 Apr 1930 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 27 Jan 1955 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 11 Feb 1955 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 12 Feb 1962, reply included (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 22 May 1962 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 12 Mar 1963, reply included (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - 26 Mar 1963 (Sc 7, Folder 2)
  - undated (Sc 7, Folder 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Advertisement for The Spoken Word's "Contemporary Poetry Series" (Sc 7, Folder 3)
  - Bookplates, 2 copies (Sc 7, Folder 3)
  - Programs
    - Alumni Association of the City College of New York Annual Dinner, 10 Nov 1953 (Sc 7, Folder 3)
    - Youthbuilder Service in New York public schools Tenth Year Dinner, 08 Oct 1947 (Sc 7, Folder 3)
  - "A Tribute to Dr. Elias Lieberman" to be read at the Testimonial Luncheon (Sc 7, Folder 3)
- Writings
  - Works by Lieberman
    - "The Accent is on Victory" (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Ballade of the Heraclitan Flux", appeared in Spirit in 1966 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Credo", appeared in Paved Streets in 1918 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "I Am An American", appeared in Everybody's Magazine in 1916; also appeared in Paved Streets in 1918 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Lincoln Was a Tall Man", appeared in the Herald-Tribune in 1943 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Mental Slumming", appeared in The Hand Organ Man in 1930 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Notation in Haste", appeared in Atlantic Monthly in 1957 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Record the Living Word", Christmas card for 1964 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Remembered Teacher", appeared in the New York Times in 1961 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "School in the Good Old Days", appeared in the New York Times on 14 Sep 1964 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "To My Brothers Everywhere", appeared in the Saturday Review in 1945; part of To My Brothers Everywhere, published in 1945 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - "Victory", appeared in The Hand Organ Man in 1930 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
  - Works by others
    - James Gibbons Huneker manuscript, 4 pages (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - Notes on poems presented anonymously at the Poetry Society of America Meeting, 28 May 1964 (Sc 7, Folder 4)
    - Reviews of Lieberman's works
      - "Announcing... Man in the Shadows" (Sc 7, Folder 4)
      - " Paved Streets" (Sc 7, Folder 4)
      - "What Critics Say About To My Brothers Everywhere" (Sc 7, Folder 4)